<section anchor="node-spf-cap-tlv" numbered="true" toc="default">
<name>BGP-LS-SPF Node NLRI Attribute SPF Capability TLV</name>
<t>
  The SPF capability is an additional Node Attribute TLV.
  This attribute TLV MUST be included with the
  BGP-LS-SPF SAFI and SHOULD NOT be used for other SAFIs.
  The TLV type is 1180. The Node
  Attribute TLV contains a single-octet SPF algorithm as defined
  in <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>.
</t>
<artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|              Type (1180)      |     Length - (1 Octet)        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| SPF Algorithm |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
<t>
  The SPF Algorithm field is used to advertise the algorithm used by
  the router to calculate the paths to other routers in the BGP SPF
  routing domain.
  The SPF algorithm inherits the values from the IGP Algorithm Types
  registry <xref target="RFC8665" format="default"/>. Algorithm 0, (Shortest Path Algorithm (SPF)
  based on link metric, is supported and described in <xref target="BGP-SPF" format="default"/>.
  Support for other algorithm types is beyond the scope of this specification.
</t>
<t>
  When computing the SPF for a given BGP routing domain, only BGP nodes
  advertising the SPF capability TLV with same SPF algorithm
  are included in the SPF computation as described in <xref target="BGP-SPF" format="default"/>.
  An implementation MAY optionally
  log detection of a BGP node that has either not advertised the SPF capability TLV
  or is advertising the SPF capability TLV with an algorithm type other than 0.
</t>
</section>
    This process starts with selecting only those Node NLRI whose
    SPF capability TLV matches with the local BGP SPF speaker's SPF capability TLV value.
<section anchor="spf-algo" numbered="true" toc="default">
<name>SPF Algorithm Consistency</name>
<t>
  Within a BGP SPF Routing Domain, all routers MUST use the same SPF algorithm
  (refer to <xref target="node-spf-cap-tlv"/>). This is the responsibility of the
  administrator for the routing domain. Misconfiguration of the SPF
  algorithm (including omission) will result in the misconfigured routers not being
  included in the BGP SPF routing topology and missing routes.
</t>
</section>
<xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8665.xml"/>

