<section anchor="prefix-length-tlvs" numbered="true" toc="default">
  <name>BGP-LS-SPF Link NLRI Attribute Prefix-Length TLVs</name>
  <t>
    Two BGP-LS Attribute TLVs of the BGP-LS-SPF Link NLRI are defined to advertise the prefix length
    associated with the IPv4 and IPv6 link prefixes derived from the link descriptor addresses.
    The prefix length is used for the optional installation of prefixes corresponding to
    Link NLRI as defined in <xref target="BGP-SPF" format="default"/>.
  </t>
  <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |IPv4 (1182) or IPv6 Type (1183)|          Length (1 Octet)     |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  | Prefix-Length |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

  Prefix-length - A one-octet length restricted to 1-32 for IPv4
                  Link NLRI endpoint prefixes and 1-128 for IPv6
                  Link NLRI endpoint prefixes.
  ]]></artwork>
  <t>
    The Prefix-Length TLV is only relevant to Link NLRIs. When received with any NLRIs other
    than Link NRLIs, the corresponding Link NLRI is considered as malformed and MUST be handled as
    'Treat-as-withdraw' <xref target="RFC7606" format="default"/>. An implementation MAY log
    an error for further analysis.
  </t>
  <t>
    The maximum prefix-length is 32 bits for an IPv4 Prefix-Length TLV and  128 bits
    for an IPv6 Prefix-Length TLV. A prefix-length field
    indicating a larger value is an error and the corresponding Link NLRI is
    considered as malformed and MUST be handled as 'Treat-as-withdraw'
    <xref target="RFC7606" format="default"/>. An
    implementation MAY log an error for further analysis.
  </t>
</section>
<li>
  The prefix(es) associated with the Current-Link are installed into the
  Local-RIB using the same rules as were used for Prefix NLRI in the previous steps. Optionally,
  in deployments where BGP-SPF routers have limited routing table capacity, installation of
  these subnets can be suppressed. Suppression has an operational impact as the
  IPv4/IPv6 link prefixes and link endpoint addresses are not reachable, resulting in tools such
  as traceroute displaying addresses that are not reachable.
</li>
<t>
  When a BGP SPF speaker receives a BGP Update containing a malformed IPv4 Prefix-Length TLV
  in the Link NLRI BGP-LS Attribute <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-rfc7752bis" format="default"/>,
  the corresponding Link NLRI is
  considered as malformed and MUST be handled as 'Treat-as-withdraw'. An
  implementation SHOULD log an error (subject to rate-limiting) for further analysis.
</t>
<t>
  When a BGP SPF speaker receives a BGP Update containing a malformed IPv6 Prefix-Length TLV
  in the Link NLRI BGP-LS Attribute <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-rfc7752bis" format="default"/>,
  the corresponding Link NLRI is considered as malformed and MUST be handled as 'Treat-as-withdraw'. An
  implementation SHOULD log an error (subject to rate-limiting) for further analysis.
</t>
<tr>
<td align="left">1182</td>
<td align="left">IPv4 Link Prefix Length</td>
<td align="left">RFCXXXX ([this document]), <xref target="prefix-length-tlvs"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left">1183</td>
<td align="left">IPv6 Link Prefix Length</td>
<td align="left">RFCXXXX ([this document]), <xref target="prefix-length-tlvs"/></td>
</tr>
